Do you dare walk these steps again?
The Exorcist III is a horror film directed by William Peter Blatty.
On the fifteenth anniversary of the exorcism that claimed Father Damien Karras' life, Police Lieutenant
Kinderman's world is once again shattered when a boy is found decapitated and savagely crucified.
Lt. William 'Bill' Kinderman, played by George C. Scott.
Father Joseph Kevin Dyer, played by Ed Flanders.
James Venamun / The Gemini Killer, played by Brad Dourif.
Father Damien Karras / Patient X, played by Jason Miller.
Father Morning, played by Nicol Williamson.
Dr. Temple, played by Scott Wilson.
The Exorcist III is a 1990 American supernatural psychological horror film written for the
screen and directed by William Peter Blatty, based on his 1983 novel Legion.
It is the third installment in The Exorcist film series and the final installment in Blatty's "Trilogy of Faith"
after The Ninth Configuration (1980), serves as a follow-up and direct sequel of The Exorcist (1973).
The film stars George C.
Scott, Ed Flanders, Jason Miller, Scott Wilson,
Nicol Williamson, and Brad Dourif.
The film follows a character from the original film, Lieutenant William F.
Kinderman, who investigates a series of demonic murders in Georgetown that
have the hallmarks of the Gemini, a deceased serial killer.
Blatty based aspects of the Gemini Killer on the real-life Zodiac Killer,
one of several serial killers who enjoyed The Exorcist.
Blatty, who wrote The Exorcist novel and the screenplay for its 1973 film adaptation, conceived
The Exorcist III with The Exorcist director William Friedkin attached to direct.
When Friedkin left the project, Blatty adapted the
script into the 1983 novel Legion.
Morgan Creek Productions bought the film rights, with Blatty as director.
Initially designed to be a standalone adaptation of that novel (hence the anachronistic elements which contradict Friedkin's adaptation of The Exorcist), the final cut wound up being an official entry in the filmed series due to
Morgan Creek demanding extensive last-minute changes — including the insistence of bringing back a key cast member from the 1973 film, as well as an exorcism sequence for the climax — much to Blatty's frustration.
Though some of the original footage appears permanently lost, Scream Factory released a director's
cut closer to Blatty's vision in 2016, with footage assembled from various sources.
The Exorcist III was released in the United States on August 17, 1990, by 20th Century Fox as part of their multi-picture deal with
Morgan Creek that commenced in 1987 and concluded in 1991, when the latter switched distribution through Warner Bros.
As such, this was the only film at that point in the series
which was not distributed by Warner Bros.
until The Exorcist: Believer was released by Universal Pictures in 2023.
The film received mixed reviews from critics and grossed $44 million
domestically against a production budget of $11 million.
The film explores themes of death penalty, religion and
supernatural, suspicion of murder, investigation, exorcism.
The tone is lighthearted and dark.